Hi and welcome back to this course where in this lesson we're going to be stepping into
the world of conditional types which is a powerful feature that lets us write logic at
the type level.
So we're going to learn how to use extens to check types and the key word infer to extract
parts of them and this is where TypeScript starts to feel like a proper programming language
or types.
First of all let's talk about what exactly is conditional types.
So conditional type looks a bit like an if statement for types.
It checks whether one type extends another and then returns different types based on
that result.
So let's do an example and we're going to define a type called is string and this is
going to determine whether is a string by looking at another type so we use it utilize
to generic t for this and if type t that we're testing extends a type of string that
we're going to simply return yes otherwise we're going to return no.
Let's do an example so if we have a type of A and we don't need to specify string by
supplying the type t here as a string that's going to mean that's going to that's going
to be yes basically because it's going to come into here and we are making it a type
of string and it's going to return yes and conversely if we have another type and we call
is string and we set this to say number the course this is going to be no because it's
not extending type string so you can see what this is doing here we have a conditional
type and is effectively allowing us to write a type that's adapting based on the actual
type that's being passed in as an input and the extends key would here allows us to check
where the one type is assignable to another.
So let's do another example and this time we're going to follow on the idea and have
a little helper that's going to allow us whether a type being passed to us is in a right
or not so do type is array type t and this is where t extends a conditional type that's
any so that's how you can say we don't really care what the array is so that's why
we use the any key word here any type is bit an array we can then say it's true or
false then we can have a type a we call helper and say this is a number and array of numbers
that's of course going to say that's true and if we have a type of b and this is call
is array and this is a string without an array then of course that's going to be false.
So you can see how this conditional types are quite careful because it's perfect for allowing
us to check and build type guards or utility types and also constrain generics to help
us make sure we have a certain type of actual types coming in.
Now let's actually have a look at another way of doing this and that's to use the key word
infer so I f is infer so how do we actually use this we don't use it here as a start but
we can actually build in on top of where we have our conditional type I'm going to build
another little example here so let's have another check and do type elements type again
it's generic and we're going to check using extends and this time we are going to infuse
the keyword infer so the infer key word allows us to extract a type from a structure so it's
a little bit like having a regular expression because it's going to allow us to do some pattern
matching for types so do infer let's say we'll infer another generic type of u and so we
have an array if it is we're going to just grab the actual type that six inside our array
here otherwise we're going to grab the type t and this can look starts to look quite strange
but let me show you how this works if we have a type a a generic type a let me call
element type and let's say we have an array of strings going to it's array of strings like
this the more happens here is our type our checker is going to apply or the array but it's
going to be want to look at the actual type that's coming out of it and it's going
to return the type that's part of the arrays in this case this will return string because
that is what's part of that the type this inside the array if we take another thing and
let me do type B is element type let me say this is an array of numbers actually function
is going to return number because that's the part of the type that's of part of the
array if we do something like type C and this element type in this time we don't supply
a an array we just say number then this is also going to return number because it's
going to come into our conditional but rather than extract the type of that's part of
the array here is it's going to return the actual type itself which is coming back as
t in this case number. Now we can use this sort of little structure to allow us to write
a function to be able to flatten arrays so let's just come into here and let's build up
a helper and say type Latin this is going to take a generic type t if it's going to extends
the array we're passing through a type on ray of strings we're going to be interested
in pulling out the type on that array if we have a type of integers and array of types
can be quite difficult to or confusing to explain as well otherwise we're going to just
get the type of t past it let's do type A do you call our flatten helper we're going
to supply an array of strings and then this will become or infer the string which is
part of the array and if we call our flatten again and we pass it number then this is
also going to return number but rather than coming as part of the u because this is
not an array it's going to return type t which is number so you can see that we are kind
of stripping out if we happen array we're flattening it and just pulling out the existing
type so it's pretty much the same as what we did before but this is more of a real
world situation where you might want to use this actual conditional type so conditional
types let us write logic pretty much at the type level we've learned how to check type
we've extends we've also learned how to extract types even infer and also build some
dynamic examples with utilities next up we're going to learn about the type cards which
use like us to safely narrow types at runtime